This programme contains
strong language.
So. what made you decide
to leave and come to Moscow?
Because I'm fed up with lying
to the public
about what's really going
on at GCHQ. where I work.
I've done 50 years of service
and I've had enough.
It's time for me to stand up
and say my piece.
50 years of services
and I've had enough.
It's time for me to stand up
and say my piece.
And what is that?
You were friends. weren't you?
That we're no different to what
we're always accusing you lot of.
Hi. Sorry?
You were friends.
Yeah. At least I thought so.
So. what are you looking for?
I don't know.
A clue. Anything.
I just can't believe he'd do this to us.
Us?
He goes missing at the same time
as the biggest leak in intelligence history.
He turns up in Moscow
and admits it on Russian television.
I'd have thought that was
enough evidence...
even for you.
You mean I should get back to work?
That's OK. Saara.
I think we all gave up hope a while back
of you ever actually
doing any work around here.
Can I take this chair?
Don't people hate
having their grammar corrected?
I mean. doesn't it just make
everyone hate you?
If we wrote code as sloppily
as we write English.
it would never run.
Some things have to be right.
Is that all you're having?
I'm Muslim.
They don't have anything halal here.
They won't be very welcoming.
What's funny?
No different to any other
department here. then?
Different FROM any other department.
It's "different from". "compared with".
No different FROM any other
department.
It's "different from". "compared with".
Different from. compared with.
Because I'm fed up with lying to
the public about what's really
going on at GCHQ. where I work.
I've done...
stand up and say my piece.
And what is that?
That we are no different to what
we're always accusing you...
Yes! What is it?
He said "different to".
He would never say "different to".
He would never make that mistake.
It can't be him.
What? S-Saara. wait.
Where is he?
Danny's on his way to London. Saara.
Shit.
Kathy?
She's not here.
Where is she?
She's gone. What do you mean. "gone"?
What did you say to her?
I didn't say anything.
I came back and she was packing.
She's been recalled to Maryland.
She flew about 25 minutes ago.
She left this.
What's going on. Saara?
Don't lie to me this time.
You're in love with her. aren't you?
Don't lie. please.
I don't know.
M-Maybe.
Have you made love here?
Yes.
OK.
Where does that leave us?
Do you still love me?
Did you ever really... love me?
Don't go. James. please. I'm sorry.
I...
I know you just lost your dad
and I know you're upset.
and I know you say you can't
deal with your emotions.
I've tried to make allowances.
I really have.
But when you crash into
people's lives. people get hurt.
People who care about you.
People who love you.
Just try and think about that?
Fuck.
Mark. welcome.
Sorry I'm late. It's fine.
I'm sure I don't need to tell you
the effect of the Yeabsley leak is...
devastating.
Most of our tools have been
rendered nugatory
and will have to be built again
from scratch.
Our priority now is to keep
what little we do have left secure.
As of 2000 hours today. Eastern Time.
the NSA's intelligence-sharing
arrangement with the UK
is withdrawn. for the foreseeable future.
Er. Mark...
signals cooperation between
our two countries...
goes back 75 years and it plays a vital...
This decision comes from the
Commander-in-chief personally...
and is not open for discussion.
The question we're all asking
ourselves here is why the hell
you re-employed
a loose cannon like John Yeabsley
in the first place.
Hiya. Hi. You all right?
Where do you want me. Sarge?
Get yourself round the back.
Make sure no press are trying
to get in through the garden.
Hey. You're gonna need a mask. Sandy.
I'm just going straight through.
thank you.
Hiya.
Sorry. Thanks.
James. it's me again.
Please call me back.
I know you're angry.
We need to talk.
Come on.
GCHQ intelligence analyst
John Yeabsley.
seen yesterday on Russian TV
admitting responsibility
for a massive leak of GCHQ secrets.
could Not have been in Moscow
yesterday. Back to Dan.
Yes!
Yes. yes. yes. I knew it.
I knew it... in light of what police
are saying here tonight.
the interview shown yesterday
on Russian TV
seems likely now. somehow.
to have been faked.
as he was clearly already dead.
here in Cheltenham.
when he was supposedly being taped
in Moscow.
Dear. A mountain of code.
Perhaps it will make you. er...
check your assumptions.
Remember the Nigerian prince.
If you find yourself scouring through
thousands and thousands
of lines of code.
that's probably...
exactly what they're expecting you to do.
Don't.
Do something else. unexpected.
You have to think outside the box.
If you can't. then you have to
find someone... who can.
Should I offer to help?
No. she doesn't need any help.
She knows exactly where
everything is. Don't you. dear?
It's the first time we've had one
of Gabe's work friends to visit.
Isn't it. Gabe?
We'd almost given up hope.
Sorry?
He was turned down by
so many employers before GCHQ.
We moved here so we could look
after him.
He can't live alone. obviously.
I know you said you didn't want to
help me any more but I'm in trouble.
What kind of trouble?
What I'm saying is...
I've got GCHQ into trouble.
OK. what I mean is...
I didn't realise I was being used.
I think there's
a third-stage malware. Gabriel.
hidden inside the code. I need to find it.
Someone tried to warn me about it.
that it was really dangerous. but...
it's only now
I think I know what he meant.
Who warned you?
That's not important now.
There's been a massive leak of data
from GCHQ. right?
Incredibly damaging.
I think that's what the third stage does.
I think there's some hidden part
of the original malware
that was built to steal our data.
But I can't find it.
I've been back through the code
line by line. There's nothing.
That's the puzzle. Gabriel.
I'm asking if you'd...
It's OK. Saara. I get it.
Where are you going. Gabe?
Sorry.
But what about the curfew?
It's obfuscated. You don't need to... Wait.
I was just trying to say you don't
need to waste time on it.
The original code's obfuscated.
They included all this garbage
so that anti-virus software
wouldn't recognise it as malware.
How many lines of garbage?
I don't know. Thousands?
We stripped them out
so we could work on it.
Tea? But before you stripped them out.
you tried to get it to run in a sandbox.
That's right. How did you know?
What happened?
Nothing. It didn't run.
They designed it so that it...
I... think it did.
It didn't. Gabriel.
I tried it again and again.
It just sat there.
I watched. Nothing happened.
You need to learn to look at
the garbage in a different way.
It's all about patterns.
Finding the code
hidden within the garbage.
But in this case.
it's more complicated than normal.
Usually.
there'd be one character of code.
And. say. five characters of garbage.
In that case.
you just need to write a script
to read one character in six.
So you're saying it's not all garbage?
Then...
there's where the number of real
code and garbage characters vary
according to a regular pattern.
Say one in four. then one in three.
then one in two. And back up again.
And that's what we've got here
in the BT code? No.
This is more complicated.
Here. there's no simple pattern.
The code characters
and garbage characters vary
according to an algorithm.
So. we can't extract the hidden code
unless we know the algorithm?
I've worked out the algorithm.
That's what took me the time.
There's your third stage.
Hidden inside of what you thought
was just garbage.
That's a data scraper.
That's how it mined our files.
That must be the MAC address
of your sandbox.
That's how it broke into our system.
It can't be.
Yes. I think so.
But how could they possibly know that?
A MAC address is like a fingerprint.
How could someone in Russia
know the address of a particular
computer at GCHQ? It's impossible.
No. it's obvious. Obvious? How?
Someone must have told them.
OK. Even if that is true.
it doesn't explain
how they got the data out.
This malware doesn't communicate.
It exfiltrates as email.
The data goes out as attachments.
The emails get lost in the flood of
all our other email traffic.
No-one notices.
They've moved on from NSA exploits.
by the way.
Now they're taking our own stuff.
What? The emails are still going out.
What?!
They must know what we're doing.
Every time I cut a link to a domain.
they set up a new one.
We're losing a massive amount
of data every second.
The scraper you found in the garbage -
can you shut it down.
stop all this at source?
Of course. Then do it.
Please.
Is that it? Yes.
You've stopped it?
Of course.
Why do you sound so surprised?
You're brilliant.
I owe you an apology.
You're right. You do.
I'm sorry.
What you did last night was amazing.
As well as in Bradford.
the central Mosque in Southall
was fire-bombed
while a service was taking place.
A spokesperson for
the Muslim Council of Britain
blamed the attack. one of dozens
reported in the last 36 hours.
on the breakdown in public order
in the aftermath of the disputed election.
What is it?
They're attacking mosques again.
My brother works at a mosque
in Swindon.
Well. you should go.
We read about it every day in the papers
and on our phones.
we hear about it on the radio.
we speak about it every morning
with our neighbours.
we watch it every night on the TV news.
And. of course. when they're
attacking us in the streets.
when they're burning our mosques...
we want to strike back.
Why wouldn't we?
It's only human.
It sounds easy. brothers and sisters...
as do all the words of Shaytan.
He speaks to us when we're angry.
He fans the flames
of our completely reasonable anger.
which comes from fear...
and the desire to protect those we love.
But we don't protect them.
brothers and sisters.
by meeting violence with violence.
Violence only breeds more violence.
more hatred.
We hit back and they hit us again.
even harder.
The way of Allah. Subhanahu wa-ta'ala.
is the harder way.
the more courageous way.
The voice of Shaytan rages in our ears.
blasting out all other sound.
You will hear the voice of Allah.
Subhanahu wa-ta'ala...
when you are quiet...
when you are at rest...
when you are at peace.
Saj?
Hey. what's up?
Shut the door. Yeah.
What is it?
I've just been speaking to
the Prime Minister.
Apparently. MI5's found some
compromising material
on the Foreign Secretary's laptop.
What kind of material?
I'm not sure.
They're sending it over. the laptop.
Inappropriate communications
with someone inside
the Russian government -
that's all I've been told.
Highly prejudicial to national security.
For fuck's sake.
Surely even they must know
that's a Russian plant?
I don't know.
It looks authentic. apparently.
None of the usual signs of
crashing around inside a computer.
If it's a plant. it's a clever one.
hard to prove.
Anyway. she's had to resign.
We're being played. aren't we?
Have been. At every stage.
Yeah. Yeah.
And very convenient that we should
lose our best friend in government
at this precise moment.
Secretary of State for Defence.
I said after the BT attack that.
if we didn't respond robustly.
we'd be hit again and we have been.
Our election has been undermined and
our most sensitive secrets stolen.
By any measure. this constitutes
the cyber equivalent
of an armed attack on
the United Kingdom.
An act of war.
Head of operations. GCHQ.
I'm not disagreeing
that a strong response is required
but you should be aware that
if you decide upon
a symmetric cyberattack.
it will be highly escalatory.
Truth is. they've been one step
ahead of us. provoking us.
anticipating how we'll react
at every stage.
It's vital that we do not react
as expected now.
We should be careful of empty gestures
that have profound consequences.
Empty gestures?
Yes. Especially if there are other
motives for doing it.
What other motives?
Can I speak frankly?
Of course.
To shore up the position of a government
whose legitimacy has been questioned.
To distract attention.
Is that what you think is going on here?
With the greatest respect
to our colleague from GCHQ.
Prime Minister.
that is a completely
outrageous suggestion.
This country has either faced
an attack amounting to
an act of war or it hasn't.
And if it has. it is our duty
as the properly constituted
government to respond.
It's nothing to do with legitimacy
or any other political considerations.
Can I just remind us that
the then Attorney General
made our red lines absolutely clear
in his 2018 speech?
Use of cyber to manipulate the
electoral system
explicitly constitutes
an intervention in our domestic affairs.
If. after that speech. we do nothing.
we are basically saying it's OK
to just roll your tanks into London.
Yes. I see your point.
Of course. if we retaliate.
we might expose some of
the things we ourselves are doing.
within Russia's critical
national infrastructure.
Which would leave us open to
the accusation of double standards.
But if that is the way you wish
to go. Prime Minister.
Danny can lay out some further options.
We don't need your options.
The Army will be taking
the lead this time.
Good luck with that.
What was that?
Nothing.
Good. Because Russia has effectively
declared war on this country.
And we. those of us around this table.
are charged with
the defence of this nation.
I require your support to do so.
David.
I'm sending you a team
from the National Cyber Force.
I want you to build them an attack.
targeting the Russian arms industry.
And I want it done today.
Can you do that?
Put them out of action?
We can certainly try.
It's time to show us what we've
been paying for at GCHQ.
All this money we've spent. It's
time to show us what you can do.
I'm sorry. Saj.
You were right.
I should've thought more carefully
before I took the job at GCHQ.
About the consequences for our family.
I over-reacted.
No. You didn't.
You were right.
I shouldn't have gone there.
I've made a mistake.
At work. What mistake?
I suppose you can't say?
I did something... that...
I thought was really clever.
It wasn't.
It was incredibly stupid and gullible.
And it's allowed something terrible
to happen.
Are you sure?
Because you always think
everything's your fault.
You have no idea.
Anyway. Dad was my fault.
What? How is that your fault?
He killed himself.
He killed himself because I went
away to uni and left him.
No. Saar... He did. I abandoned him.
No. that's not what happened.
Saar... Yeah. he killed himself.
He didn't kill himself.
I mean. sorry to ruin this
"I'm to blame for everything"
thing you've got going. but no...
he didn't kill himself.
I mean. if you'd... come home
you'd know that.
It was an accident.
A signalman made a mistake.
He sent a goods train up a line that
was supposed to be out of service.
Dad took a short cut across the track
and the train hit him.
It wasn't suicide.
You're just saying that
because suicide is haram. No.
I swear on Mum's life -
that's what happened.
You may have behaved like a shit
not coming to see him
but he didn't commit suicide.
I liked your sermon.
Thanks.
I mean. I...
I agreed with...
I agreed with everything you said.
Do you think I should resign?
That's up to you. but...
we'd be losing the last real voice
of moderation around the table.
There'd be nobody left
to protect the staff.
Well. what about you? Me?!
They'd sack me 15 seconds after
you're out the door.
Sorry. They're ready.
"They're ready."
I told Barbara to take the kids.
go and stay with her parents in France.
You're joking. No. absolutely not.
It's not that bad. is it?
I don't know. But I'm pretty sure
this - us attacking them -
it's exactly what they want us to do.
You have to ask yourself why.
Do you think I should get Freddie out?
Maybe.
Ready. boss.
OK. what happens now?
You stand aside
and we press the button.
That way it's covered by the rules of war
and you don't end up in The Hague.
OK. Finn. Up you get.
Control-E.
How long will it take to have an effect?
No time at all.
It's happening now.
Is this real?
Real?
I doubt it.
Danny. can I have a word with you?
What is it?
Private word.
What is it? Our comms are down.
Sorry? All our comms are down.
I wanted to speak to you out here
because I didn't want to create a panic.
What. just Army comms?
To be honest. we're not sure.
I managed to get through to the MOD
on one of your landlines.
They're requesting
that GCHQ help re-establish contact.
With...? With UK Armed Forces.
Sorry. Danny. The Defence Secretary
is on the line.
Which channel?
No. I mean he's actually
on the line. He's on the phone.
Richard. We've just heard.
Heard what?
About your loss of comms.
Not that.
The nuclear submarine control system
is unresponsive.
It may have been hacked.
What?
Are you... Are you absolutely sure?
Richard?
If there's anything
still working around here.
try and get me NSA up on
the satellite. er. on this one. OK.
I've decided to leave...
OK.
But if you've made a mess.
don't leave before you've cleared it up.
You should never leave someone else
to clear up your mess. Saar.
Mitch.
Danny.
Look. I know you guys aren't talking
to us at the moment
but I thought you should know
somebody just hacked our
nuclear submarine control system.
What? You're kidding?
Plus... all of our military comms
are down.
The Russians have just spent
the last two hours
exaggerating the effect of
a very targeted attack
on a couple or arms factories
to make whatever it is they're doing
look like self-defence.
And my guess is. they've been
planning this for a long time.
Yeah. the problem is
we're seeing those images
of hospital fires too. Danny...
Yeah. they're fakes. Mitch.
Well. they look pretty real to us.
I've gotta tell you.
there's not a lot of warm feelings
towards you guys here at the moment.
We could really do with
some help right now. Mitch.
Next. please. Come on through.
Arms up. please.
You can't use that in here.
You can't use that here. Turn it off. now.
OK. But I've got to write this down.
Have you got any paper?
Saara. wait.
I've got nothing to say to you.
Please.
I think you're about to be attacked.
The UK. I've got something
to give you that will stop it.
I don't believe you. Vadim.
It's just another provocation.
Anyway. I thought you said
in Harrogate they'd kill you.
I don't care any more.
I don't care what happens to me.
This is too important.
Look at this.
What is that?
It's you. At your desk in GCHQ.
OK. You hacked the CCTV.
So what? What does that prove?
Saara. please. There isn't much time.
You have to trust me.
You have to think outside the box.
What?
What did you say?
JSSO's showing unidentified aircraft
entering our airspace
and none of the other systems are
showing it.
The RAF don't seem
to have been scrambled yet.
But it is possible we are under attack.
But it's just another hack.
isn't it? Fake news?
What if it's real this time.
you know. like crying wolf?
How can we take that chance?
What. an invasion? Why not?
We've been underestimating Putin
for ten years.
All the way through we've been
asking. what's the bigger picture?
The one thing we've never considered
is that he might just
be insane enough
to have territorial ambitions.
What if this whole thing is about
separating us
from Europe and the Americans
so that when this moment came.
we'd be alone?
Not now. Saara.
Danny. you absolutely HAVE
to come and see this. Right now.
It's the CCTV - so what?
Saara. I don't have time for this.
You have to turn it off. Please.
I can't show you what I've got
to show you until you turn it off.
Shut down the CCTV.
Really?
Yeah. Do it.
They hacked the system.
The FSB were watching
everything we're doing.
They can't. It's air-gapped.
How do you know?
Cos I've just been inside their computer.
I'm sending you something now.
Two things.
You can use them
to trade with the Americans.
to bring them back in.
As soon as that happens.
Putin will back down.
During this first phase.
we are degrading the capability
and resolve of our enemy.
as well as discrediting his institutions
and leadership with espionage.
assassination.
manipulation of social media.
cyberattacks.
faking of imagery.
all with the aim of
creating disillusionment.
confusion and. and... And chaos.
By the time war is openly declared.
the enemy's ability... War?
To defend himself will be
significantly reduced... Danny?
We're receiving a data dump.
Where from?
Russia.
OK. let's go.
Strategic situation. His relationships
with his allies are
fatally undermined. one by one.
It's mostly code. There's terabytes of it.
I think it's the FSB's
offensive cyber exploits.
My God!
This puts us back in the game.
So. how... How this all is to be achieved?
How do you ensure that.
the final phase. the war is won?
The war is won using a technique
called reflexive control.
This is the predetermining
the enemy's behaviour
in Russia's favour.
We define our ultimate objective.
We define our ultimate objective -
the total defeat of our enemy.
Subtitles by Red Bee Media